Hello, I'm Graeme Fitch and I'm coming to you from Steinway Hall in London for Pianist magazine
and this is the third video in the series of three videos on practicing for a performance
and what we need to do when we know we're going to have to perform something, decide whether we're
going to play from memory or not and do some preliminary research on the background to the
piece. This is just, I'm just recapping now what we covered already in the first two videos and
then after we've done a little bit of analysis of the piece and found the shape, the patterns,
we can embark on some serious deep learning techniques that we use to learn the notes and
to finesse the playing and I'm just going to show you a few of these ideas by way of recap
and I've chosen here Scarlatti's Sonata in C K 5 1 3, just the last section, the
the presto section, which probably would go at something like this tempo
so
something along those lines, it could be a bit faster, could be a bit slower, your choice really
okay so what would I do first? Well maybe the first approaches that I would take would revolve
around the the three s's, slowly or a variety of different speeds, separately and that can be
something as simple as hands separately but it could also be strands separately, you know elements
that we find, horizontal elements and then sections and the idea of working in sections is so that we
don't overload our working memory, we take a little chunk of music and we stop after we've
done what it is we were going to do. Let me show you some of this in action so if I take, I'm going
to do a slightly more sophisticated type of separate practice, I call it zigzag, I notice that
the right hand at the beginning here and then the left hand are playing the same material so I'm
going to play the first four bars right hand and then the next four bars left hand
so
I could have done that better, I'm not going to do it again but I would do that until I was
happy with that and it might mean that I'd want to do a little bit of controlled stops
and then and then stopping on the first note of each bar. What about the other hand?
So that's separate practice done in a I think a quite a creative way, zigzagging from one hand to
the other. So controlled stops would be something like in this particular example perhaps two bars
and one note. Now evaluate that, assess that, was it correct, in other words were the notes right,
was the rhythm right, fingerings, dynamics, character, anything else you want to add to
that list but don't forget to ask yourself did it sound good and did it feel good because if it
didn't feel good we can't pass that so your inner quality control inspector has to be able to sign
that off. Yes and you may decide you want to repeat it. Why would you repeat it? Well to enjoy
playing it fluently and to form a habit.
Right now I can graduate and go to the next spot
and I was noticing then that just at the very end of the second bar
my left hand wasn't entirely comfortable. I'm going to do that again focusing on my left hand
and I got a much freer movement from the low G pinky G to the higher G so you can
see what I'm doing here is I'm finessing and refining as I go along and these are deep
these are some deep learning techniques that we've been looking at previously
but the rest of this video is going to be free of demonstration because I'm going to describe to you
what I would recommend doing as soon as you know that you've got a performance you would know the
date. If you're preparing for let's say a diploma examination you'd want to set a date. We have to
remember Parkinson's law. Parkinson's law says that says that work expands to fill the available time
so if you've given yourself six months to complete a task it's going to take six months.
If you give yourself six weeks provided it's realistic time frame it's going to take six
weeks. If you say well I'll take my diploma when my pieces are ready believe me they will never be
ready. You need to give yourself some sort of a deadline so let's assume that you've got
a performance the beginning of December for example. What you'd want to do at least six
weeks before that you'd want to be fully ready. I recommend six weeks so that everything is ready
you're comfortable you're fluent and at that point you organize three run-throughs
three trial run-throughs of the program for other people preferably on pianos that you don't know
because you're going to in your performance you're more than likely going to have to deal with a
piano that's unfamiliar in a setting that's unfamiliar so you have to have practiced
doing that you have to have practiced as much as you can three safe run-throughs even if the piano
is bad the run-through will be valuable to you so that's you've put that in your diary so you
you would put that in for middle of October and then you'd work backwards from there when is the
first run-through going to be for yourself in relation to your you know time frame so you'd
set that more or less that doesn't have to be absolute but you'd have a rough idea that three
or four months after you start let's say you're going to have a run-through for yourself and the
first run-through for yourself I'm assuming now it's a program of pieces you're probably going to
be quite disappointed oh that's no nowhere near how I practiced it that's fine because the first
run-through will be full of problems and issues and dissatisfactions and all sorts of things
what you would then do would be to embark on a process of practicing a performance for yourself
followed by reflection where you sit with the recording of the piece if you've made a recording
and I advise that doing that sometimes and just flagging up spots where you were happy oh yes that
really came out I like the way that my right hand melody projected my pedaling was nice and clean in
that spot don't forget to comment on the positives and flag up those corners of the piece or the
program that didn't quite stand up and make bullet points on a piece of paper so that you've got
something to work from when you do your spot practice now the spot practice deals with the
areas of weakness in the previous run-through so let me go through that again you practice
the performance and you start at the beginning and you go right to the end whether you're happy
or unhappy you have to stick with that then you do your reflection and then you have a separate
practice session where you do spots where you practice for yourself those corners the next day
or perhaps two days later you go through exactly that process again and I like to do that daily
for a week then I embark on maintenance practice that could be maybe going back to a little bit of
memory boosting work it could be a little bit of slow practice I could use some of the practice
tools that I used when I first started learning the piece because we pianists never stop working on
accuracy and finesse and you know we never get to the to the end of that journey just like a gardener
can never say my garden is finished now I just have to sit back and enjoy it with always tinkering
with it so then do you see where this is coming from what what what you'll have done by doing this
is you'll have practiced playing from the beginning of your program to the end of it
first for yourself and then for a group of safe audience it could be friends family your teacher
or you know perhaps something that you organize in a church hall something like that and that will
prepare you for your final performance you'll find that after the three run-throughs the first will be
the second maybe a little better and the third you'll be starting to feel I think I'm on top of
this and between that and the performance itself you've got to make sure that you keep a positive
mindset I quite like to use affirmations something like I'm thoroughly prepared for my performance
and I fully deserve to enjoy it and you either say that out aloud repeat it you could you could
think it but have these statements that you make and believe them I'm fully prepared for my
performance and I deserve to enjoy it you do remember one thing that if you're enjoying your
performance so will your audience and in the end when when you're playing for an audience don't
worry about mistakes mistakes are insignificant wrong notes are insignificant as Beethoven said
but to play without passion that's inexcusable so what we want to do is to throw caution to the
wind when we perform let go there will be a few accidents a few little slips a few wrong notes
it's fine but if you can focus on communicating the message of the music to the audience then you
will have succeeded thank you very much for watching I do hope this helps you on your journey
and I'll look forward to seeing you again very soon